A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Projects FA733
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Projects
1950-1964
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA733
41 microform reels 41 reels of 16mm microfilm.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Custodial History note
Although Project Files are recorded for 4,237 projects in the Fund File Index, the Ford archive's series of Project Files on microfilm currently only includes 984 Project Files (plus 1 NY Fund file, NY-79). Some of the missing 3,253 Project Files were renumbered as Grant Files (with 'PA' numbers) after 1953, but the majority of the missing files seem to have been destroyed.
Other Finding Aids note
Project files are indexed in the Ford Foundation's Central Index cards, 1950-1974 (FA736). However, not every Project file recorded in the Central Index is included in the Ford archives.
The Ford Foundation's Central Index, Master Cards – Projects (FA736) provides descriptions of Project files numbered 'NY-1' to 'NY-166', and 'A-1' to 'E-199', and is arranged by Project number. The 'Master Cards' for Project files provide the only remaining detailed description of the destroyed Project files.
Scope and Contents
Most of the remaining Project files document project proposals rejected by the Ford Foundation from 1950-1964. Project files for accepted proposals were re-numbered as Grant files, with a Program Action (PA) number. The new Grant file number (PA number) is noted on the Ford Foundation's 'Central Index (FA736), Master Cards - Projects' cards, under the old Project number.
The exception being the 'Ford Foundation initiated' projects, which remained as Project files after being approved. For instance, "C-488: Social Sciences and Business Administration (Ford Foundation initiated, 1958".
Arrangement note
Project Files are housed on 41 reels of 16mm microfilm numbered P-1000 to P-1040.
Project Files are arranged and identified by an alphanumeric Project number beginning with the letters A thru E, followed by a sequential number between 1 and 1000 (for example: A-001 to E-999).
Project Files are numbered chronologically.
Missing Title
1950-1952 A-1 to A-1000
1952-1956 B-1 to B-1000
1956-1959 C-1 to C-100
1959-1963 D-1 to D-1000
1963-1964 E-1 to E-237
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- A-60: Thessalonica Agricultural and Industrial Institute (American Farm School), 1951-1952 (Reel P-1000)
  Scope and Contents
  Project to extend the service of the American Farm School in Salonica, Greece, through systematic follow-up and assistance to its graduates, for the purpose of increasing agricultura production and improving standards of living in their rural communities.
- A-809: Public Administration Training in Pakistan - Prime Minister Khawaja Nazimuddin, 1952-1957 (Reel P-1000)
- A-825: Non-profit book corporation for more effective use of books in Asia & Near East (Ford Foundation initiated), 1952-1953 (Reel P-1000)
- A-847: Mission to Near East - Report of working party on the Near East, recommended projects, country reports, etc. (Ford Foundation initiated), 1951-1953 (Reel P-1000)
- A-848: Mission to the Far East - Indonesia, Burma, etc. (Ford Foundation initiated), 1952 (Reel P-1000)
- A-868: Women United for the United Nations - Support for newspaper service, 1951-1957 (Reel P-1000)
- A-924: Exchange of education teams between India and the United States - Ministry of Education, India, 1952 (Reel P-1000)
- A-949: Public Administration Training for India - Indian Finance Ministry, 1952 (Reel P-1000)
  Paul H. Appleby suggested as consultant for Public Administration Training for India project.
  Related Materials
  See also Ford Foundation grant file# PA54-117 (05400117), reel# R-0885.
- A-989: Pilot Project in Rural Village Development, Turkey, 1952 (Reel P-1000)
- A-993: Establishment of a Center of Arab Studies, 1952-1954 (Reel P-1000)
- B-20: Pilot Project in Elementary Education - Saudi Arabia, 1952-1953 (Reel P-1000)
  Preliminary development of this project must include the following: (1) initial definition of the project itself, and (2) preliminary negotiations paving the way for the visit of a high-level group which it is suggested include Mr. Henry Ford II, to negotiate directly with the King of Saudi Arabia on the project.
- B-29: Social Science Research Council: Survey of Research on Conservation and Resources, 1952 (Reel P-1000)
  To make a survey of Research on Conservation and Resources in government - federal and state - and in colleges and universities; the survey of federal government research will be made by Dr. Arthur Maass in Washington by direct contact with the federal agencies, and the survey of state research will be made by questions circularized to the states through the Council of State Governments and the Association of State Planning and Development Agencies.
- B-30: The Conservation Foundation: Survey of Conservation Education, 1952 (Reel P-1000)
  To arrange for the preparation of a series of papers on conservation education and to synthesize in a brief report o the Ford Foundation the most important views expressed in the papers and to give the Conservation Foundation's assessment of the overall situation; also to assist in the review of papers at a meeting of the National Committee on Policies in Conservation Education.
- B-31: University of Chicago: Gaps in Resources and Conservation Research, 1952 (Reel P-1001)
  To support Dr. Schultz's activities on the identification of gaps in resources and conservation research; for assistants and to gring colleagues to Chicago for conferences; and for the work of his seminar.
- B-32: Social Science Research Council: Research Liaison Office - Middle East and Southern Asia, 1952-1954 (Reel P-1001)
  To aid an assist in a general way a wide range of people coming into the area for work and study, and to give more specialized help to research students in their special fields.
- B-45: Social Science Research Council, American Political Science Association, Public Administration Clearing House, National Planning Association, National Civil Service League, and National League of Women Voters: Commission of Inquiry on Public Service Personnel (Reel P-1001)
  To establish a Commission on the Public Service, composed of nationally representative leading citizens, to make a basic re-examinational and restatement of the concepts upon which our public service is to be built; the basic purpose of such a restatement would be to provide the guidelines for public policies which will (1) preserve our substantial gains against the patronage system, and (2) move public personnel management forward toward the goals of a more responsible and more flexible public service.
  See Ford Foundation grant number 05400093 for subsequent material.
- B-69: Indian Ministry of Education and Community Projects Administration: Social (Adult) Education Program for India, 1952-1953 (Reel P-1001)
  See also Ford Foundation grant numbers PA53-45, PA53-46, PA53-47.
- B-86: Evaluation of Programs to Improve Personnel in Behavioral Sciences, 1952 (Reel P-1001)
- B-89: Contingency Fund for Unanticipated Fellowships in Behavioral Science, 1952 (Reel P-1001)
  See also Ford Foundation grant numbers PA53-118, PA53-119, PA53-120, PA53-121, PA53-122, PA53-123, PA53-124, PA53-125.
- B-109: Economics and the Behavioral Sciences, 1952-1954 (Reel P-1001)
- B-146: Board on Overseas Training and Research (BOTR): Survey of Foreign Personnel Requirements, 1952-1953 (Reel P-1001)
- B-151: Government of Pakistan: Evaluation of Pakistan Village Improvement Program, 1953-1956 (Reel P-1001)
- B-152: Research and development fund for small projects in the behavioral sciences, 1953 (Reel P-1001)
  See also Ford Foundation grant numbers PA53-18, PA53-78, PA53-79, PA53-145, PA54-7.
- B-160: Youth Working Conferences in India, 1953-1954 (Reel P-1001)
- B-162: Social and Economic research - India, 1953-1956 (Reel P-1001)
- B-171: Near & Middle East Committee of Social Sciences Research Council: Integrated Research Program for Near East and Middle East, 1952-1954 (Reel P-1001)
- B-196: Roosevelt College, Chicago, Illinois: African Studies Program, 1953-1957 (Reel P-1001)
- B-210: Study on the U.S. Tariff Structure and its Effect upon International Trade, 1953 (Reel P-1001)
- B-220: College for Advanced Studies for the Arab Area, 1953-1954 (Reel P-1002)
  See also Ford Foundation records, Projects, file #A-993.
- B-326: Puerto Rican Economic Development Administration: Economic Development in Puerto Rico, 1953 (Reel P-1002)
- B-333: Government of India, National Extension Service: Village Youth and Women's Activities in India, 1953-1954 (Reel P-1002)
- B-358: Ohio Wesleyan University, Denison University, The College of Wooster, Oberlin College: Intercolleges Program of Eastern Studies, 1954-1958 (Reel P-1002)
- B-372: European Leaders Exchange, 1954-1955 (Reel P-1002)
- B-383: Support for the American Committee for Émigré Scholars, Writers, and Artists (American Council for Emigres in the Professions, Inc.), 1953-1954 (Reel P-1002)
- B-394: Republic of Haiti: Haitian Development Program, 1954 (Reel P-1002)
- B-404: Fund for the Advancement of Education: Support for Continuation of Faculty Fellowship Program & High School Teacher Fellowship Program, 1954 (Reel P-1002)
- B-407: Vermont Higher Education Council: Development of the Study of Non-Western Cultures, 1954-1958 (Reel P-1002)
- B-447: New School of Social Research: Support for the New School of Social Research, 1954-1958 (Reel P-1002)
- B-489: Ford Foundation Indonesian office (Jakarta Field Office): South Asian Seminars, 1956 (Reel P-1002)
- B-490: Ford Foundation Indonesian office (Jakarta Field Office): Higher Education for Indonesia (Basic Education for Physical and Economic Development of Indonesia), 1955-1956 (Reel P-1002)
- B-503: Government of Afghanistan: Survey of the Needs of Afghanistan, 1954-1956 (Reel P-1002)
- B-524: Training of Foreign Nationals, 1955 (Reel P-1002)
- B-536: University and College Internship Program in Administration, 1955 (Reel P-1002)
- B-545: Establishment of Institute for International Social Work, 1955-1957 (Reel P-1003)
- B-569: Ruth Sloan Associates, Inc. - Survey of Economic, Social, and Educational Projects in Africa, 1955-1957 (Reel P-1003)
- B-584: Publications in Public Administration for Governments of Near East, 1955-1956 (Reel P-1003)
- B-625: Program Specialist - Consulting Economist Wolf Ladejinsky to Government of India (Land Reform Program), 1954-1955 (Reel P-1003)
- B-659: Study of India's Community Development Program by World Leaders in Community Development, 1955-1956 (Reel P-1003)
- B-678: Grants-In-Aid Program in the Behavioral Sciences, 1955-1956 (Reel P-1003)
- B-739: Community Development Program - Indonesia, 1955-1958 (Reel P-1003)
- B-749: Inter-American Legal Studies, 1955-1957 (Reel P-1004)
- B-764: Soviet and East European Travel by Scholars, Teachers, and Trainers, 1955-1956 (Reel P-1004)
- B-766: University of Michigan - Juvenile Delinquency: A Study of Etiology as Guide to Prevention and Treatment, 1955 (Reel P-1004)
- B-779: Conferences on the Teaching of International Relations, 1955-1957 (Reel P-1004)
- B-780: Relationship between Engineering and Administration, 1955-1957 (Reel P-1004)
- B-797: Thesis Fellowships for Doctoral Candidates in Economics and Business Administration, 1955-1956 (Reel P-1003, Reel P-1004)
  See also Ford Foundation Grant number PA56-307.
- B-798: Research Fellowships for Teachers of Economics and Business Administration, 1955-1956 (Reel P-1005)
  General
  A duplicate copy of this files is housed on reel P-1006.
- B-799: Fellowship Program for Master of Business Administration (MBA) Graduates, 1955-1956 (Reel P-1005)
- B-818: Support to the American Association for the United Nations, 1955-1957 (Reel P-1005)
- B-873: European Cultural Center (Centre Européen de la Culture) - Support for Asian-European Cultural Conference under the direction of Denis de Rougemont, 1956-1958 (Reel P-1005)
- B-894: Midwest Psychological Field Station of the University of Kansas - Research in Psychological Ecology, 1956-1957 (Reel P-1005)
- B-896: Program in Medical Education, 1956-1957 (Reel P-1005)
  See also grants to medical schools for "ENDOWMENT TO HELP STRENGTHEN INSTRUCTION AT PRIVATE MEDICAL SCHOOLS - GENERAL SUPPORT" (grant file numbers 05601100 through 05601144), and grant to National Fund for Medical Education (grant file number 05700098, or PA57-98).
  Request: $90,000,000. Program is divided into 2 parts:
  A. Direct grants to medical schools to be held for a period of 10 years in an endowment fund. B. Indirect grants to medical schools through a grant to the National Fund for Medical Education (NFME).
- B-900: Educational Television - Stimulation of Program Resources in Colleges and Universities, 1956-1963 (Reel P-1005)
- B-935: San Francisco Bay Area Council - Support for a San Francisco Bay Area Regional Plan and Studies Program, 1956-1958 (Reel P-1005)
- B-941: Study of Management Education, 1955-1959 (Reel P-1005)
- B-945: Support to Advanced Training for Faculty of Indonesian Universities, 1956-1957 (Reel P-1006)
- B-953: Support of Publication for University Presses, in the Humanities and Social Sciences, 1956-1960 (Reel P-1006)
- B-970: Support to Program of American School of Classical Studies, Athens, Greece, 1954-1957 (Reel P-1007)
- B-971: American Council on Education - Support to Commission on Education and International Affairs, 1956-1959 (Reel P-1007)
- B-979: University Administered Fellowship Funds for Study in Asian Studies, Near Eastern Studies, Soviet Studies, and East European Studies, 1956-1959 (Reel P-1007)
- B-992: Program of Regional Cooperation Among Colleges and Universities, 1956-1957 (Reel P-1007)
- C-22: Support to Continuing Committee on Muslim-Christian Cooperation, 1956-1958 (Reel P-1007)
- C-23: Rotating research professorships in economics, 1956-1959 (Reel P-1007)
- C-37: International economic studies, 1956-1959 (Reel P-1007)
- C-45: Education of American children overseas, 1956 (Reel P-1007)
- C-64: Provision of books to public and private institutions in Indonesia, 1956-1959 (Reel P-1007)
- C-65: Cultural development and cultural exchange program - Indonesia, 1956-1959 (Reel P-1007)
- C-90: International Movement of Catholic Students - Support for African student seminar, 1956-1959 (Reel P-1007)
- C-95: Boston University - Research on mental health and delinquency, 1956-1959 (Reel P-1007)
- C-96: Dartmouth College - Applications of mathematics to the social sciences, 1956 (Reel P-1007)
- C-101: University of Pennsylvania - Support to foreign policy research institute, 1956-1958 (Reel P-1007)
- C-122: University of Chicago - Fellowship program for Latin American economists, 1956-1958 (Reel P-1007)
- C-146: Program Specialist: Consultant on procurement of scientific laboratory equipment - Indonesia, 1956-1959 (Reel P-1007)
- C-152: Support for four American universities working on sister relationships with Indian universities, 1956-1957 (Reel P-1007)
- C-158: City College of New York - Research on problems of middle age, 1957 (Reel P-1007)
- C-164: Social Science Institute, Washington University, St. Louis - Support research on social context of learning, 1957 (Reel P-1007)
- C-165: National Association of Housing and Redevelopment Officials - Support research on low-income public housing, 1957 (Reel P-1007)
- C-167: Flint Child Guidance Clinic (Flint, Michigan) - Research in mental health, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-168: University Institute for Experimental Medical Research, Oslo Norway - Support for research and studies of circulatory disturbances, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-171: Pennsylvania State University - Support for longitudinal study of attitude formation and change (Reel P-1008)
- C-173: Board for Fundamental Education - General support for the Board for Fundamental Education, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-179: University of California, Graduate School of Business Administration - Research and planning of instruction in administration and problem solving aspects of management, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-180: University of Puerto Rico - Development of graduate studies in college of social sciences, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-182: Western College for Women, Oxford, Ohio - Support for summer seminar trips for faculty, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-184: Harvard University - Support research in international economics, 1957-1958 (Reel P-1008)
- C-185: Establishment of Au Service de l'Education des Adultes, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-186: New York University - Support for an institute of international philosophy, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-187: Children's Special Services Center - Support for Children's Special Services Center of Brattleboro, Vermont, 1956-1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-188: Washington University, St. Loius - Suppoort for center of urban research, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-190: America-Israel Society - Pilot program to supplement the benefites of the Fulbright Act, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-193: Citizens Public Personnel Association - Support for research in the improvement of governmental personnel administration, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1008)
- C-196: Yale University - Support for international and foreign economic studies (Reel P-1008)
- C-198: National Academy of Religion and Mental Health - Support for the National Academy of Religion and Mental Health, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1008)
- C-199: Human Relations Area Files - Social science research program for Pakistan, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1008)
- C-202: Columbia University - Support for microfilming of Turkish archives, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1008)
- C-208: University of California, Berkeley - International economic studies, 1957-1958 (Reel P-1008)
- C-209: Institute of International Education - Support program of exchanges in the arts, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-210: Harvard University - Reorganization & cataloging of Trotsky archive, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-211: The People-to-People Foundation, New York - Support for People-to-People program, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-212: Museum of Modern Art, New York - Support program of intercultural exhange, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-214: Support for publishing house for publication of "Kultura", 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-217: Washington University, St. Loius - Support expanded civic ecucation program, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-218: Washington University, St. Loius - Support endowed professorship programs in the social sciences, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-219: Brigham Young University - Research in teaching of modern languages, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-221: University College of the Gold Coast - Support for training for citizenship project, 1956-1959 (Reel P-1008)
- C-224: Wallace Clark Center for International Management of New York University - Support for international extension of management "Know How", 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-225: Brown University - Support study on problems of business survival, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-227: Purdue University - Support for leave for research re: "Management planning by mathematical programming", 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-228: Lake Forest College - Support for study of application of the anti-trust laws to regulated industries, 1957-1958 (Reel P-1008)
- C-231: Columbia University - Support for research in historical methodology, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-234: New York University - General support for School of Commerce, Accounts, & Finance, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1008)
- C-237: National Council for the Social Studies - Support field study in education for international relations, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-240: American Council on Education - Support for second edition of "Universities of the World Outside the U.S.A.", 1957-1958 (Reel P-1008)
- C-241: Wayne State University - Support for a modern language audio-visual project, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-242: Brookings Institution - Study of post war negotiations for the regulation of armaments, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-243: University of California, Los Angeles - Support program of international and foreign studies, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-244: Support program of recruiting university graduates for Indonesian civil service, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1008)
- C-245: National Planning Association - Support for study of role of Puerto Rico in technical cooperation programs of United States and international agencies, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-246: University of Connecticut - Support graduate work in the humanities, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-247: Grinnell College - Support study of delinquency among Spanish-American youth in New Mexico, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-248: Stanford University - Study of national income and expenditures of selected underdeveloped countries, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-251: State University of Iowa - Scholarship & exchange program for high school and junior college teachers, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-253: University Cooperative Housing Associates, Inc. - Support for low cost student housing, scholarships & grants-in-aid, 1957 (Reel P-1008)
- C-259: Stanford University - Support for Center for Study of International & Comparative Economics, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1008)
- C-260: Ministry of Education, Government of Indonesia - Development of pilot projects in area of compulsory education, 19571959 (Reel P-1009)
- C-261: Columbia University - Support for International Institute of Insurance Law and Administration, 1957 (Reel P-1009)
- C-263: Edward W. Hazen Foundation - Support for conference on Asian-American relations, 1957 (Reel P-1009)
- C-264: Government of Indonesia, Ministry of Education - Support adviser to University of North Sumatra on building construction plan, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1009)
- C-271: University of Michigan - Seminar for research & training in international economic & economic development, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1009)
- C-275: Government of India, Ministry of Cooperatives - Food & Agriculture - Support for program of planning & rebuilding villages of India, 1957-1958 (Reel P-1009)
- C-276: Government of India, Ministry of Cooperatives - Food & Agriculture - Support for 14 pilot projects for rural cooperatives - India, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1009)
- C-280: Government of India - Support for program of development of small industries - India, 1957 (Reel P-1009)
- C-282: Program specialist in economic research at University of Rangoon -, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1009)
- C-287: University of Chicago - Support for program in English for foreigners & teaching of English, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1009)
- C-291: Agricultural Bank of Iran - Agricultural credit cooperatives, Iran, 1957-1958 (Reel P-1009)
- C-292: Tulane University - Support program in Latin American studies, 1957 (Reel P-1009)
- C-293: Washburn University - Support for project in education in the Behavioral Sciences, 1957 (Reel P-1009)
- C-294: Association of Better Business Bureaus, Inc. - Support for Better Business Bureau film program, 1957 (Reel P-1009)
- C-301: Det Udenrigapolitiske Selskab - Support for foreign policy society, Denmark, 1957-1959 (Reel P-1009)
- C-302: Manhattan College - Support to liberal arts education program, 1957 (Reel P-1009)
- C-304: Greater New York Council for Foreign Students - Support for information center for foreign students, 1957 (Reel P-1009)
- C-308: University of Chicago - Support for socio-psychiatric study of university student, 1957 (Reel P-1009)
- C-314: University of Rome - Support for National Institute for Economic Research, 1957 (Reel P-1009)
- C-315: Armenian Missionary Association of America - Support for Haigazian College at Beirut, 1957-1963 (Reel P-1009)